This video is supported by Omaze, click the link below for a chance to win two seats on board one of Virgin Galactic's first flights into space!
自人类航天起步以来 只有大约六百人见过这番景象
Since the beginning of spaceflight, only around 600 people have seen this view.
太空一直是只有极少部分人才能去的地方
Space has always been a place reserved for a tiny portion of the population.
成为宇航员 往往要付出一生的努力
Being an astronaut is something that would usually require a lifetime of commitment.
先要在学校选对专业 然后成为一名经验丰富的飞行员
From taking the right subjects at school, getting flight experience as a pilot -
最终才能被宇航局招入麾下
to finally being accepted into a space agency.
属实是花钱都换不来的东西
It's one of the few things in life that even money couldn't buy.
但现在 “宇航员”的定义渐渐有了改变
But now the definition of 'astronaut' is starting to change.
一般来讲 “宇航员”这个词的含义是
For most of its existence, this word actually meant
“为太空飞行而进行过训练的人”
someone who had been trained to travel in a spacecraft.
所以如果你没去过太空 但通过了一切所需的训练
So even if you hadn't actually gone into space but passed all of the necessary training,
那你也是一名宇航员
you were technically an astronaut.
但随着太空旅行产业伊始
But now with the beginning of space tourism,
对上太空的人的需求已经完全改变了
the requirements for people travelling to space have completely flipped.
那些登上维珍银河或者蓝色起源飞船的人
Those wishing to hop on board either Virgin Galactic or Blue Origin's space vehicles
几乎不用经过训练 但必须要有钞能力
will require almost no training, but they will require a lot of money.
尽管如此 还是有上百人已经订购了船票想要体验一把太空人的感觉
Despite this, hundreds of people have already bought tickets for the experience to become astronauts.
但这和之前那些去过太空的有钱人有什么区别呢？
But how is this any different from the other millionaires that have paid their way into space?
2001年 美国企业家Dennis Tito
In 2001, American entrepreneur Dennis Tito
花了2000万美元去国际空间站进行了一次8天的旅行
paid $20 million for an 8-day trip to the International Space Station.
当时NASA认为让游客进太空不太好
At the time, NASA thought it was inappropriate for tourists to go to space,
所以拒绝训练他
so they refused to train him.
所以活让毛子接了 他和两名毛子宇航员搭乘联盟飞船TM32任务前往太空
Instead, he partnered with the Russian's and took a ride on Soyuz mission TM32 along with two Cosmonauts.
从那以后 就开始有很多百万富翁花钱上飞船
Since then, various millionaires have paid for rides onboard space vehicles.
但时代变了
But things are changing.
太空旅行脱离了政府公家的航天局
Space tourists are now moving away from the typical government space agencies
转而向民营企业靠拢
and partnering with private companies.
为了让太空旅行这个产业能做大做好
In order for space tourism to become a thriving industry,
企业需要拉低订票门槛 让普通人无需任何训练就能上船
it needs to be as easy as booking a plane ticket - without the need for any training.
但民营企业又不能随便把人射到太空
But a company can't just launch people into space without permission.
就像民航飞机一样 所有飞船也要经过FAA许可
Just like traditional aircraft, each vehicle needs to be approved by the FAA,
才能运载大众旅客
in order for it to start flying regular passengers.
FAA管的挺宽 从传统民航 到商业航天旅行都归他们
The FAA is in charge of regulating all aspects of aviation,
from traditional passenger airlines to commercial space travel.
因为上太空的飞船一定会经过民航会用的空域
Since space vehicles share the same airspace as airliners,
FAA要负责让区域净空 保护老百姓
the FAA is responsible for making sure everything is carried out safely and that the public are protected.
但FAA在航空旅行和太空旅行上的管理却有很多不同
But the FAA's involvement with air travel is very different to space travel.
从数量上看 FAA每年要管1650万架次的飞行
To put it into perspective, the FAA handles around 16 and a half million flights per year.
但放到航天领域 今年一共发射次数大概只有50
In the space world, the number of launches expected to take place this year is around 50.
但现在 太空旅行越来越多 发射数量也会急剧增长
But now that space tourism is becoming a real thing, this number will start to grow rapidly.
更不要说太空叉在搞的Starship亚轨道旅行了
Not to mention SpaceX's grand plan for suborbital passenger travel using their Starship rocket.
他们要在全球各地搞海上发射台
They want to operate offshore launch platforms all around the globe
每天运送上千名旅客
with thousands of passengers travelling each day.
以当前FAA的规章 这是完全不可能的
With the FAA's current rules, this would be impossible.
美国企业在全球任何地方发射火箭都需要FAA许可
If you're an American entity launching a rocket anywhere in the world, you need an FAA license.
但获取许可这件事是要花时间的
But getting a license isn't a quick process.
公司提交申请文件 FAA要花上半年去审查
Once a company files an application, it can take the FAA up to 180 days to review it.
整个流程包含大量的测试与认证工作 全部完成后才能放行
This process involves a huge amount of testing and verification before they can give the all clear.
整个手续包含四款不同的规章条例
The assessment is broken down into 4 different regulatory parts,
每款都有一系列严格的安全需求
each with their own set of strict safety requirements.
火箭要有发射中止系统
The rocket needs to have a flight termination system,
可以在火箭偏离预定路线后自毁
which will purposefully blow up the rocket if it goes off course.
让火箭从一个装满燃料的二踢脚炸碎成无数更细小的碎片
This turns the rocket into much smaller pieces of debris rather than one enormous tank full of fuel.
如果你想建一个太空港 FAA还会做一系列的环境方面的审查
In order to operate a spaceport, the FAA also needs to do intense environmental checks
确保火箭发射不会影响当地野生动物
to make sure rocket launches won't destroy or disrupt any nearby wildlife.
许可发下来 也要求必须是指定火箭从指定地点发射
Even if a license is granted, it only covers that particular rocket for that specific location,
假设该火箭在所有发射中都遵循类似的轨迹
assuming that the rocket will follow a similar trajectory for all of its launches.
如果火箭要换个地方发射 就要重新申请许可
If a rocket is to be launched from a different location, a new license is needed.
所有这一切都要花费大量时间——
All of this takes a lot of time -
而随着民营航天企业的飞速成长
and as private space companies continue to make huge advancements,
FAA的规章制度已经显得落后了
the FAA is starting to fall behind.
这点从太空叉最近的几次Starship测试中就能看出
This became very evident with SpaceX's recent Starship tests.
2020年12月 太空叉尝试发射Starship原型机并让其着陆
In December 2020, SpaceX were attempting to launch and land their first ever Starship prototype.
FAA和太空叉交涉过 并给了他们发射许可
The FAA had worked with SpaceX and granted them a launch license,
但他们只能在一定的天气条件下发射
but they could only launch under certain weather conditions.
在SN8上天几分钟前 FAA告知太空叉取消发射
Just minutes before SN8 took off, the FAA told SpaceX to cancel the launch.
而太空叉在任务控制中心的员工无视了这条消息
SpaceX employees at mission control ignored this message,
因为他们认为天气良好 FAA的监察员只是没有拿到最新的气象数据
since they thought the weather was fine and that the FAA inspector didn't have the latest weather data.
那次震撼的发射后 SN8重着陆后发生爆炸
After an impressive launch, SN8 had a hard landing and ended in a massive explosion.
虽然没人受伤 但FAA因为太空叉无视了自己的命令而表示I'm angry
Although no one was injured, the FAA were angry that SpaceX had ignored their launch requirements.
还启动了对太空叉的调查 不过最后他们也没损失什么
This prompted an investigation into SpaceX but ultimately never cost them much,
FAA也同意后续的Starship发射了
as the FAA were happy for them to launch several other Starship's after this.
不过FAA的确规定以后博卡奇卡发射Starship时必须有一名监察员在场
They did however stipulate that an FAA inspector must be present for every flight of Starship from Boca Chica.
这导致了SN11发射的推迟
This led to the launch of SN11 being delayed
因为FAA的监察员咕咕咕了
because the FAA inspector couldn't make it down to Boca Chica in time.
太空叉未经许可开始建造发射架时又和FAA打起来了
SpaceX clashed with the FAA again when it started building a launch tower without permission.
这个150米高的塔式结构将用于吊装巨大的Starship组件
This 150 meter tall structure will one day lift and catch enormous Starship sections.
在太空叉的赶工下 这个建筑盖得飞快
The structure itself went up extremely quickly, with the usual SpaceX urgency.
但FAA警告太空叉说 环境审查完成后 这个塔可能要大改
But the FAA warned SpaceX that it might need to drastically change the tower
once the environmental review is complete.
太空叉说我不听我不听 还是加班加点修塔 修周边设施
Despite this, SpaceX continues to build the tower and the surrounding infrastructure at an incredible pace.
在快速变化的发射计划下
With a rapid and ever changing launch schedule,
这些规章制度严重阻碍了太空叉的发展
these kinds of requirements stand in the way of SpaceX's progress.
马一龙认为这放到以后是个大问题
Elon Musk sees this as a big issue for the future.
他认为FAA的规章都过时了 放过去可能说得通
He claims that the FAA's rules are outdated and only made sense in the past,
因为在以前 一年的发射也没几次
when there were only a handful of rocket launches every year.
大家都承认FAA在航空业的贡献
No one is arguing that the FAA isn't a great thing for airplanes.
但如果我们每天全世界有上百发火箭发射的话
But if we want to have hundreds of rockets launching and landing each day around the world,
那FAA就必须对他们的运行模式进行改革
the FAA will need to drastically improve the way it operates.
而FAA也的确在行动
But that's exactly what it's doing.
为了赶上创新的步伐
In order to catch up with the pace of innovation,
FAA正在努力简化航天公司的手续
the FAA is now working to streamline the process for space companies.
那四款规章条例现在已经被简化为一款
Those 4 parts of the rule book have now been condensed down into a single part
适用于所有商业航天飞行活动
for all commercial spaceflight.
航天公司现在可以申请航天器运营商许可证
Space companies can now apply for a vehicle operator license,
拿着这一个许可 就能从多个发射场发射火箭了
which will allow them to fly from multiple different launch sites under the same license.
如果太空叉想做亚轨道旅行项目的话 那这个许可至关重要
This will be crucial if SpaceX are to go ahead with their Earth to Earth travel idea.
虽然坐Starship旅行这件事看起来还很遥远
Although the idea of Starship Earth travel may seem far away,
但类似的亚轨道旅行却已经实现了
the same kind of suborbital passenger travel is already happening.
维珍银河和蓝色起源都成功送乘客进入了太空
Virgin Galactic and Blue Origin have now achieved their goals of flying passengers to space.
经过近20年的努力 两家公司竟然在同一个月达成了这个目标
After trying for nearly two decades, amazingly, both companies achieved this goal in the exact same month.
但他们也和太空叉一样要面对FAA这一硬茬
But the FAA was just as much of a hurdle to them as it was for SpaceX.
最开始 维珍银河的许可只包含了专业飞行员和宇航员的测试飞行
Initially, Virgin Galactic's license only covered test flights with professional pilots and astronauts.
不过最近他们把许可更新为了完整的商业发射许可
However, this license was recently updated to a full commercial launch license,
可以带乘客飞了
allowing them to start flying passengers.
这对于那些已经买了票打算上太空的六百来人是个好消息
This was good news for the 600 people that have already bought tickets for a ride into space.
FAA要求他们在正式开始前再做两次额外的测试飞行
The FAA requires them to do two additional test flights before they can start doing their own thing.
一旦之后的测试飞行圆满完成 那你们的机会就来了！
Once the remaining test flights have been completed successfully, it could be your chance to go to space.
猝不及防的工商时间……
Omaze is giving away two free seats on one of the first Virgin Galactic flights to Space!
In the history of humanity, just 600 people have been into space and now you could be one of them.
During the flight, you and your guest will experience weightlessness as you hover above our planet at 80km,
with a view like never before.
And if going to space wasn't enough for you, you'll also get a VIP tour of Spaceport America,
the incredible facility from which your journey will begin.
For your chance to win two seats on one of the first Virgin Galactic Flights to space,
go to Omaze.com/primalspace and enter now.
You can choose to make a donation which will support charities by giving away life changing experiences like this.
That's Omaze.com/primalspace.
Go there, donate and good luck!
如果您想支持本频道 欢迎来Patreon赞助我们
If you'd like to support the channel even more, consider becoming a Patron,
可以让你的名字出现在视频结尾 并能加入我们的Discord群
where you can give your input on each video and join our exclusive Discord server.
非常感谢您观看本期视频 我们下期视频见
Thank you very much for watching and I'll see you in the next video!